<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe treatise declaring the true noble-man, and the base vvorldling. By Walter Sweeper minister of Strowd</title>
            <author>Sweeper, Walter.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13234</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23526</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113865</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849094</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849094</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14227</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13234)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14227)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1467:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe treatise declaring the true noble-man, and the base vvorldling. By Walter Sweeper minister of Strowd</title>
                  <author>Sweeper, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones, dwelling in Red-crosse streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14227:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14227:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE TREATISE <hi>DECLARING</hi> THE TRVE NOBLE-MAN, <hi>AND</hi> The baſe Worldling.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. SAM. 2.30.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>They that honour me, I will honour: and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be deſpiſed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Walter Sweeper</hi> Miniſter of Strowd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by WILLIAM IONES, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Red-croſſe ſſtreete. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14227:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14227:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM EARLE OF PEMBROCK, and <hi>Philip</hi> Earle of Mountgomerie, Grace, mercie and peace from God the Father through Chriſt. (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y good Lords, I had intended to haue preſented to your hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Ladie-mother, now at reſt with God, the firſt fruits of my labours in this kind, containing a iuſt defence of Gods truth and the credit of Dorts Synod againſt ſome of <hi>Arminius</hi> his ſchollers here at home, who will not be reclaimed by the graue ſentence of that late Councell, nor affrighted with the ſtrange death of their maiſter: but as <hi>Arrius</hi> his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, after his fearfull death did labour to ſcatter his errors farre and neare, ſo do theſe with vs. But
<pb facs="tcp:14227:3"/>your Honours may obiect to me, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. To which I anſwer, that partly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and partly the importunitie of ſome enemies did draw me forth both by preaching and printing to aſſay to ſtop the mouthes of gainſayers. Now I humbly offer to your Lordſhips view the true Chhriſtian Noble-man, who by the Spirit of Adoption calleth God <hi>Abba, Father,</hi> Rom. <hi>8.15.</hi> and which <hi>Iob</hi> ſtiles Chriſt, Iob <hi>19.25. Goeli, My redeeming kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> and with <hi>Iſay,</hi> Iſa. <hi>5.1. Dodi, My neere kinſman.</hi> Your Honours may beſt challenge this little Treatiſe as your owne right, becauſe that I gained the greateſt part of my litle learning through my acquaintance with your honorable fathers houſe and family, where you had a moſt religious and truly noble breeding and education, by the zealous care of your pious and truly religious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Ladie <hi>Bathſhebah</hi> neglected not to teach her yong <hi>Lemuels</hi> humane and diuine knowledge, Prou. <hi>31.1, 2.</hi> Your truly noble fathers houſe for ſtate and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment ſomewhat reſembled <hi>Salomons</hi> Court, <hi>2.</hi> Chron. <hi>9.4.</hi> where <hi>Shebaes</hi> Queene obſerued the meate of his table, the ſitting of his ſeruants, and the atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his miniſters. And your famous Wilton houſe, like a litle Vniuerſitie was a more excellent nurcerie for learning and pietie, then euer it was in former times, when King <hi>Edgars</hi> daughter <hi>Editha</hi> had her reſidence and regencie there: ſo that Popiſh <hi>S.F.E.</hi> had no need to ſeek the reſtoring of it to its former vſes. Wilton houſe had in it that godly learned Phiſitian and skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Mathematician M. Doctor <hi>Moffet</hi> my moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and kind friend; it had in it great <hi>Hugh Sanford</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14227:3"/>learned in all arts, ſciences, knowledge, humane and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, <hi>vſque ad miraculum,</hi> whom I euer obſerued as <hi>Horace</hi> did his <hi>Maerenas</hi> euer before him, <hi>ſingul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim pauca locutus,</hi> from whom I neuer departed without ſome profit. To paſſe ouer <hi>Gerard</hi> the Herbal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, M. <hi>Maſſinger</hi> and other Gentlemen ſchollers. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer noble houſe had ſucceſsiuely deeper Diuines, namely Biſhop <hi>Babington,</hi> B. <hi>Parry,</hi> M. <hi>Conna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> M. <hi>Walford,</hi> M. <hi>Parker,</hi> M. <hi>Bigs.</hi> In this noble Houſe <hi>Babingtons</hi> rules of pietie and honeſtie ſwayed, ſwearing was ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; yea the houſe-keepers and inferour ſeruants well knew and practiſed the grounds of Religion, as <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> commendeth the ploughmen of Paleſtina for their Halleluiahs. Theſe were the Trophees of your fathers houſe; he honoured God, and God honoured him, and you his ſeed enioy the bleſsing: whereas the ſeed of the wicked, <hi>lo ijqqare le holam,</hi> ſhall not be famous for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Iſa. <hi>14.20.</hi> The ſeed of the righteous ſhall be great or ſtrong in the earth, <hi>Dor ieſharim ieuorach,</hi> the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the vpright ſhall be bleſſed, Pſal <hi>112.1, 2. Wiſedome with an inheritance is good,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> Eccleſ. <hi>7.12.</hi> God hath bleſſed your Honours with a goodly heritage, Pſal. <hi>16.6.</hi> The price of wiſedome is in your hands, Oh let your hearts be to it, Prou. <hi>17.16.</hi> To whom much is giuen, of them much is required, Luk. <hi>12.48.</hi> You cannot ſay with the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q> Nor with <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> in <hi>Homer,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14227:4"/>
            <p> Serue the Lord with ioy of heart for the aboundance that hee hath giuen you, Deut. <hi>28.47.</hi> Let your houſes not be like <hi>Eugenius Tertius Bernards</hi> ſcholler his houſe, <hi>&amp; recipiant &amp; faciant bouos.</hi> Oh let the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained faith, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes to <hi>Timothy, 2.</hi> Tim. <hi>1.5.</hi> that dwelt in your good father, dwell in you.</p>
            <p>The Lord bleſſe your Honours, and increaſe in you all the graces of his holy Spirit, for his Chriſts ſake, in whom I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruant,</hi> Walter Sweeper.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14227:4"/>
            <head>THE TRVE NOBLE-MAN.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>The Text,</hi> Prou. <hi>12.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Righteous is more excellent then his neighbour: but the way of the wicked ſeduceth them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE three bookes of <hi>Solomon</hi> are by ſome compared to the three parts of the Temple; the Prouerbes to the large Court, made for the aſſembly of all the people, wherein Chriſt walked, Ioh. 10.23. Eccleſiaſtes to the holy place where the Prieſts ſerued the Lord, Luk. 1.9. and the Canticles to the moſt holy place, whereinto the High prieſt onely went once a yeare, Leuit. 16.12. Though this b granted, yet the authority and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of this booke is no whit diſparaged, but may well anſwer the beautifull gate of the Temple, Acts 3.2. being giuen by diuine inſpiration as all other Scriptures, 2. Tim. 3.16. And <hi>Solomon</hi> wrote not this booke by any priuate motion, but as he was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the Spirit of God, 2. Pet. 1.19, 20, 21. And
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14227:5"/>the title <hi>Miſhle</hi> in the Hebrew, much commen deth to vs the excellencie of this booke, coming of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal,</hi> to rule, excell, or ſpeake graue ſentences, or dark parables, Ezek 20.49. <hi>Memaſhal Meſhalim hu, Doth he not ſpeake parables?</hi> and it is as much as <hi>Kurieuein,</hi> princely to rule, Rom. 6.4. or, <hi>authentein,</hi> to exerciſe authenticke authoritie, 1. Tim. 2.12. becauſe theſe ſentences, both in regard of their diuine matter and forme, do far excell other writings of this kind. The Ethicks, O Economickes and Politickes of all Heathen Philoſophers, muſt giue place to theſe. A great part of theſe Prouerbes, were copied out by <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> ſeruants, Prou. 25.1. A good patterne for religious Courtiers. Now whereas <hi>Solomon</hi> wrote 3000 parables and 1005 ſongs, 1. King. 4.32. God in his gracious prouidence hath reſerued to the vſe and edification of his Church, onely theſe few ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prouerbs, with Eccleſiaſtes and the Canticles, ſuffering the other bookes of humane wiſedome, whereof we reade 1. King. 2.41. to periſh, and not willing to clog the Church with many bookes. And therefore many things done by Chriſt, are omitted, Ioh. 20.30. becauſe otherwiſe the world would not containe the bookes that ſhould be written, Ioh. 21.25. And as we reade Eccleſ. 12.12. <hi>There is no end of writing bookes; and much reading is a weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you will know the ſumme and ſcope of this booke, it is to teach man the holy knowledge of God, diuine dutie and morall precepts of ciuilitie, Prou. 1.1, 2, 3, 4. For pietie doth not ouerthrow the duties of ciuilitie: as we learne from Chriſt, Luke
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14227:5"/>14.7. both teaching inward humilitie and outward courteſie, in not ſeeking the higheſt place at feaſts, thereby to preſerue our credit.</p>
            <p>Now in the perſwading to true holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, the holy Ghoſt vſeth theſe two chiefe motiues: Firſt he ſheweth the excellencie of the knowledge and feare of God, in it owne nature. Secondly, the good effect of it, making the godly and righteous truly happie, as in this my text, <hi>the righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zadick,</hi> righteouſnes is either attributed to God, as he is in himſelfe ſimply iuſt and infinitely good, Math. 19.17; ſo in the Angels ſong, Iſay 6.3. he is proclaimed thrice <hi>Holy,</hi> rather to proue his infinite holineſſe, then the trinitie of the perſons.</p>
            <p>Secondly, righteouſneſſe is applied to God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he doth impute vnto vs Chriſts righteouſnes, Rom. 10.3.26. 2. Cor. 5.21. Secondly, Chriſt our Mediator is called Gods <hi>righteous ſeruant,</hi> Iſay 53.2. and Zach 9.9. <hi>Sions righteous King;</hi> and Acts 4.27. Gods <hi>righteous Child, the immaculate Lambe of God,</hi> 1. Pet. 1.19.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Angels and ſoules in heauen are called <hi>holy and iuſt,</hi> Math 25.31. Heb. 12.23. But my text ſpeaketh not of theſe, but of a righteous man in this life excelling his wicked neighbour. And the truly conuerted Chriſtian is called righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: Firſt in regard of Chriſts righteouſneſſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to him, Iſay 50.8. <hi>He is neere that doth iuſtifie me:</hi> He doth iuſtifie the wicked, Rom. 3.26. who being iuſt by faith liueth, Rom. 1.17. Secondly, we are iuſt in regard of infuſed graces and renewed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14227:6"/>obedience. And the word <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> ioyned with <hi>holineſſe,</hi> is ſtrictly taken for the duties of the ſecond Table, Luk. 1.74. <hi>Seruing God in holineſs and righteouſneſſe.</hi> Sometimes it ſignifieth both pietie and charitie, yea all the duties of the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table; ſo <hi>Noah</hi> is called <hi>righteous,</hi> Geneſ. 6.9. Of both theſe righteouſneſſes, firſt, Chriſts impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ours wrought by Gods Spirit and word, faith is an inſtrument: for, Rom. 1.18. <hi>The iust by faith liueth:</hi> and Acts 15.9. <hi>The Gentiles heart was pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by faith:</hi> and Acts 26.18. <hi>They are</hi> alſo <hi>ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by faith in Chriſt.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather commeth of a verbe ſometime ſignifying to abound; ſo the French hath it, <hi>A plus de reſie:</hi> and the note is, more liberall in gifts; but the clauſe following ouerthroweth this ſence. Sometime it ſignifieth to remaine, Eccleſ. 1.13. <hi>Mahijthron, What remaineth. Iunius</hi> hath it, <hi>What profit is there of all the labours.</hi> But in my text it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth to excell; as Gen. 49.3. <hi>iether ſeeth veiethur gnazi, Excellencie of dignitie and my ſtrength: altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou ſhalt not be excellent.</hi> The laſt word <hi>reugth,</hi> ſignifieth a friend, a companion, but here a neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
            <p>A man iuſtified by faith, ſanctified by Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is more excellent then his wicked neighbour. You ſhall haue the ſence of the other clauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>My text containeth in it two propoſitions: firſt, The righteous man is more excellent then his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked neighbour. The ſecond: The proſperous way of the wicked, maketh him to erre both in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and in courſe of life. The firſt propoſition
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14227:6"/>teacheth, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label> that <hi>An holy and religious man truly fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God, by the ſentence of God and iudgement of the Church is more excellent then his irreligious neighbour, though neuer ſo great in the eye of the world.</hi> More briefly theſe two Doctrines:
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, <hi>The godly man is truly honorable.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, <hi>The wicked man is truly baſe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>That this may not ſeeme like ſome of <hi>Tullies</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxes, affirming, that the wiſe man is only free, &amp; the wiſe man is onely rich; let vs firſt heare what God ſaith to the commendation of the righteous, what in the ſecond place he ſpeaketh to the diſgrace of wicked men: and note here with me, that here is the figure <hi>Meioſis</hi> leſſe ſpoken then is meant. For the Scripture here intendeth, that the child of God is truly honorable, and the childe of the diuell truly baſe; like to that phraſe, Eccleſ. 13. <hi>Wiſedome excelleth, folly, as light excelleth darkneſſe.</hi> Light is good, darkneſſe naught; ſo wicked men are baſe, godly men are honorable. In Iſay 4.5. the Lord promiſeth <hi>a couering defence to all the glorie,</hi> that is, emphatically, to all the glorious people of God. <hi>Honorable things are ſpoken of thee, thou Citie of God,</hi> Pſa. 87.3. The beleeuers &amp; true worſhippers of God are called <hi>Gods ſecret ones,</hi> Pſal. 83.3. Gods people are termed <hi>Se gullah, Gods choiſe and chiefe treaſure,</hi> Exo. 19.5. and <hi>Laos periouſios, A peculiar people,</hi> Tit. 2.14. The <hi>Bereans</hi> gladly entertaining the Goſpel, are ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Eugeneſteroi,</hi> more honorable then others that did not ſo readily receiue the word, Acts 17.2. <hi>There are threeſcore Queenes and foureſcore concubines, and virgins without number. My Doue, my vndefiled is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14227:7"/>but one, the onely one of her mother, ſhe is the choiſe one of her that bare her: the daughters ſaw her and bleſſed her, yea the Queenes and concubines praiſed her,</hi> Cant. 6.8. Now this that is ſpoken of the whole Church and Spouſe of Chriſt, muſt be vnderſtood of the glorious eſtate of euery holy beleeuer, who <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in vertue,</hi> and is a true <hi>Saint</hi> here <hi>on earth,</hi> Pſal. 16.2. And for this cauſe <hi>glorification</hi> ſignifieth both preſent holineſſe and future glorie, Rom. 8.39. This cauſeth the Spirit of God to preferre <hi>a poore childe</hi> walking in vprightneſſe, <hi>before an old vnwiſe King,</hi> Eccleſ. 4.13. But when <hi>he that ruleth ouer men is iuſt, and ruleth in the feare of God,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, 2. Sam. 23.3. then he is in honour another <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1. King. 3.13. who had not his peere for true honour all his dayes, of whoſe royaltie Chriſt ſpeaketh, Mat. 6.33. When <hi>a King reigneth in righteouſneſſe, and Princes rule in iudgement,</hi> Iſay 32.1. when <hi>the King is the ſon of Nobles, and Princes eate in due time, for ſtrength and not for drunkenneſſe,</hi> Eccleſ. 10.17. then <hi>the land is</hi> not onely <hi>bleſſed,</hi> but theſe great men may truly be ſtyled as <hi>Abraham</hi> was by the Hittite, <hi>mightie Princes,</hi> yea <hi>the Princes of God,</hi> after the Scripture phraſe, Gen. 23.6. Now the great Magor, the great Turk, the <hi>Cham</hi> of Tartarie, with the rich Chinaes, liuing in Heatheniſme, diſgracefully thinking and ſpeaking of our truly noble Chriſtian Princes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of pettie Princes of Chriſtendome, are like <hi>Nabal,</hi> who according to his name was a fooliſh baſe creature, and yet could ſpeake baſely of <hi>Dauid, Who is the ſonne of Iſhai?</hi> 1. Sam. 25.10. The vaſſals alſo of Antichriſt can write and ſpeake
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14227:7"/>diſgracefully of Gods annointed ones who haue ſhaken off the Popes yoke; like <hi>Shimei,</hi> who to our <hi>Dauids,</hi> are but dead dogs, 2. Sam. 16.7, 8, 9. As righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <hi>Lot</hi> was more worthy then all Sodom, 2. Pet. 3.7. as <hi>Lazarus</hi> his eſtate was better then rich <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,</hi> Luk. 16.22, 23. yea <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> in priſon more happie then inceſtuous <hi>Herod,</hi> Mark. 6.20. ſo ſtill are Gods children more honorable then the diuels. To conclude therefore the firſt kinde of proofe, drawne from the conſent of the Scripture, and to haſten to variable arguments drawne out of the Scripture, let all men know, that the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and feare of God bringeth credit and honor to all ſtates and conditions; it aduanceth the credit and eſteeme of poore men, and to honorable men by birth and calling; it is like a diamond in a ring, making them that were gold before, to become the moſt fine gold, yea <hi>Michtam</hi> the pureſt gold of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phir.</p>
            <p>The firſt argument is drawne from the God of the righteous; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> and according to the triplicitie of the perſons, it is threefold; God the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt by nature, is euery iuſt mans fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by grace and adoption; ſo in this reſpect our pedegree is from heauen, and therefore very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable. Chriſt teacheth all true Chriſtians, Math. 6.9. to pray thus, <hi>Our Father which art in heauen.</hi> All beleeuers haue this prerogatiue to be called <hi>the ſonnes of God, which are not borne of blood, nor of the will of the fleſh, nor of the will of man, but of God,</hi> Ioh. 1.12. Chriſt ſaith, Ioh 20.17. <hi>I go to my Father and your Father. We haue the Spirit of adoption, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14227:8"/>Abba, Father,</hi> Rom. 8.15. <hi>We are predeſtinated to the adoption of children,</hi> Epheſ. 1.5. God is <hi>the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of</hi> our <hi>ſpirits,</hi> Heb. 12.9. He is our <hi>heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> able and willing to giue vs all things in Chriſts name, Luke 11.13. We are commanded ſo to doe, and haue a promiſe to be heard, Ioh. 16.23. 1. Ioh. 5.14.</p>
            <p>The ſecond argument is drawne from Chriſt our elder brother, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> who maketh all his yonger bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren honorable; as the yongeſt brethren in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie, for the moſt part enioy the titles of the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the Electorſhips excepted; and the yonger bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren with vs beare the ſame coate-armour, ſome little difference, by the rules of Heraldry excepted, in regard of their ſenioritie and minoritie. Chriſt <hi>maketh vs Kings and Prieſts to his Father,</hi> Reuel. 1.6. <hi>The ſanctifier and the ſanctified are all of one; for which cauſe he is not aſhamed to call vs Brethren,</hi> Heb. 2.11. Who is <hi>the firſt borne amongſt many brethren,</hi> Rom. 8.29.</p>
            <p>For the further clearing of this point, let vs firſt ſee what Chriſt is in himſelfe. Secondly, what he is to vs. And thirdly, what he hath done to make vs honorable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt in regard of his owne naure, is <hi>Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, Counſeller, the mightie God, the Father of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi> Iſay 9.6. though at the time of his manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he ſaith, Pſal. 2.7. <hi>This day haue I begotten thee;</hi> yet after an vnſpeakable manner he was begotten from eternitie, Pro. 8.22. <hi>Ganin, He hath poſſeſſed me in the beginning of his dayes, before his workes of olde. In the beginning was the Word, and this Word was with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14227:8"/>God, and that Word was God,</hi> Ioh. 1.1, 2. which the Greeke Poet <hi>Nonnus, Iohns</hi> expoſitor, renders thus, <hi>en arreto logos arche, In the beginning,</hi> which by words cannot be expreſſed; therefore without rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery he was the Fathers equall, Philip. 2.6. yea his <hi>fellow,</hi> Zach. 13.7. <hi>God euer all,</hi> to be <hi>bleſſed for euer,</hi> Rom. 9.5. Secondly, in regard of his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he is moſt pure, holy, the immaculate Lambe of God, 1. Pet. 1.19. conceiued in the wombe of the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> by the holy Ghoſt, Luke 1.35. he ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled the whole law, the will of his Father to the vtmoſt, Pſal. 40.7, 8. <hi>he became obedient to the death of the croſſe,</hi> Phil. 2.18. ſo he became <hi>the Lord our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> Ier. 23.6. our <hi>wiſedome, righteouſneſſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption ſanctification,</hi> 1. Cor. 1.30. This (<hi>Word</hi> (I ſay) <hi>became fleſh, and Eſkenoſen, dwelt in our nature,</hi> as in a tabernacle, Ioh. 1.14. <hi>Great is the myſterie of godlineſſe, God manifeſted in the fleſh, iuſtified in the ſpirit, ſeene of Angels, preached to the Gentiles, belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued on in the world, and receiued vp into glorie,</hi> 1. Tim. 3.16. <hi>At his Name euery knee in heauen and earth, and vnder the earth doth bow,</hi> Phil. 2.10. He is <hi>ſet at Gods right hand in heauenly places, farre aboue all principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and powers, and might &amp; dominion, and euery name that is named, not onely in this world, but that which is to come,</hi> Epheſ. 1.20, 21. Now ſecondly let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what he is to the Church in regard of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, <hi>God hath put all things vnder his feete, and gaue him to be head ouer all things to the Church, which is his bodie, the fulneſſe of him that filleth all in all,</hi> Ep. 1.22.23. <hi>He is the head of the body the Church, who is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, the firſt borne from the dead, that in all things
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14227:9"/>he might haue the preheminence,</hi> Coloſſ. 1.18. <hi>Sit on my right hand</hi> (ſaith the Father to him) Pſal. 110.1. <hi>till I make thine enemies thy footſtoole.</hi> And ſo as King and Prophet he <hi>ſendeth the rod of his power out of Sion, whereby he mildly ruleth the willing people</hi> of good deuotions, Pſal. 110.2, 3. And as <hi>with a mace of iron breaketh the rebels in peeces as potters veſſels,</hi> Pſal. 2.9. And in the 4. verſe of the CX. pſalme, by an oath he is made <hi>a Prieſt for euer after the order of Melchizedek.</hi> Heb. 7.1, 2. Chriſt is <hi>the Prieſt of our profeſsion,</hi> more excellent then <hi>Moſes:</hi> he built the houſe, <hi>Moſes</hi> was but a ſeruant of the houſe, Heb. 3.1, 2, 3. The Legall prieſts were ſinfull, offered ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices for themſelues, and died; he holy and pure, and blameleſſe, liueth for euer, Heb. 7.23, 24, 26, 27. There many ſacrifices could not take away ſinnes, but Chriſts one oblation did, Heb. 9.13, 24, 26. <hi>once</hi> for all, Heb. 10.10. As our Prieſt alſo <hi>he appeareth for vs in heauen,</hi> Heb. 9.24. <hi>and maketh interceſsion for vs,</hi> Rom. 8.34.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in the execution of theſe offices, what hath he done for vs: firſt, as our Prophet he teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs his Fathers will, and giues vs holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Peter</hi> (Acts 3.22.) telleth the Iewes out of Deut. 18.15. <hi>A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe vnto you, out of your brethren, like vnto me, him ſhall you heare in all things. God laſtly ſpake to vs by his Son,</hi> Heb. 1.2. who taught <hi>Noah</hi> and all the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19. of whom the Father ſaith, <hi>This is my beloued Sonne, heare him,</hi> Math. 17.5. Secondly, this righteous King of Sion, Zach. 9.9. doth ſit as King on mount Sion, pſal. 2.6. Hee our King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14227:9"/>all our enemies, <hi>ſinne,</hi> Rom. 8.3. <hi>the law,</hi> Gal. 4.5. <hi>the diuell,</hi> Heb. 2.15. Col. 2.15. <hi>death,</hi> Hoſ. 13.14. 1. Cor. 15.53. ſo deliuereth vs from the hands of all our enemies, Luk. 1.71. Thus he ſhall beate downe all our enemies, 1. Cor. 15.25, 26, 27. deſtroying the laſt enemie, Death, ſhall giue vp the kingdome to God the Father, bring all his ſubiects to him, ſhall ceaſe to reigne then as Mediator, but ſhall retaine the glorie of the kingdome for euer, as the Angell telleth <hi>Marie, Of his kingdome ſhall be none end,</hi> Luke 1.33. As our Prieſt <hi>he died for our ſinnes, and roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for our iuſtification,</hi> Rom. 4.25. by his blood he hath redeemed vs, Eph. 1.7. Col. 1.14.20. his blood hath waſhed vs from all our ſinnes, Reu. 1.5. Thus Chriſt becomes to vs our redeeming kinſman, Iob 19.25. and our righteouſneſſe, 1. Cor. 1.30. eſpecially when he performes to vs the ſecond part of his prieſthood, by being our Interceſſor and Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, ſtil making interceſſion for vs at the right hand of his Father, Rom. 8.34. and appearing for vs in heauen, Heb. 9.24. Thus in the dayes of his fleſh he offered vp prayers for vs, Heb. 5.7. Ioh. 17.9. From his hand much incenſe mixed with the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Saints is offered to God, Reuel. 8.3. He therefore that hath this Chriſt, hath life, 1. Ioh 5.12. On him that beleeueth not, his wrath abideth, Ioh. 3.36. <hi>Our life is with God in Chriſt; when Chriſt our glorie ſhall appeare, then ſhall we appeare with him in glorie,</hi> Col. 3.3, 4. By him we are heires of heauen, Rom. 8.17. and are made meet to be inheriters with the Saints in glorie, Col. 1.12. ſo that we may ſay with the Church in the Canticles, 5. chap. 16. verſe,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14227:10"/>
               <hi>This is my beloued, and this is my friend, O ye daughters of Ieruſalem,</hi> that hath <hi>redeemed vs vnto God by his bloud, out of euery kingdome, tongue, people and nation; and hath made vs Kings and Prieſts to our God, and we ſhall reigne on the earth,</hi> Reuel. 5.9, 10.</p>
            <p>Come we now to the third argument, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> drawne from the holy Ghoſt ſanctifying vs and adorning vs with all ſauing graces. True noble men haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes true noble ſpirits, by which they are diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the baſe ſpirited vulgars: ſo the holy people of God haue Gods Spirit giuen to them, Luk. 11.13. Becauſe they are children, God ſendeth his Spirit to them, Galat. 4.6. the ſame Spirit that raiſed Chriſt from death, Rom. 8.2. <hi>If any</hi> one <hi>hath not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his,</hi> Rom. 8.9. Hence it is that <hi>Chriſt dwelleth in our hearts by faith,</hi> Epheſ. 3.17. and after our effectuall calling, <hi>Chriſt is in vs, except we be reprobates,</hi> 2. Cor. 13.5. The works and effects of the holy Ghoſt in vs are foure. This holy Spirit firſt ſanctifieth and regenerateth vs, being borne againe of water and of the Spirit, Ioh. 5.7. and borne from aboue. The word of truth, Iam. 1.18. and the immortall ſeed of the word is the inſtrument hereof, 1. Pet. 1.23. by which we are made cleane, Ioh. 15.3. <hi>The Lord doth waſh away the filth of the daughters of Ieruſalem, by the ſpirit of iudgement, and by the ſpirit of burning,</hi> Iſay 4.4. by <hi>afflictions opening the eare,</hi> Iob 33.16. and by <hi>fire purging the ſonnes of Leui,</hi> Mal. 3.3. This free Spirit affranchiſeth them and ſets them at libertie, Pſalme 51.12. from the bondage of ſinne, 2. Cor. 3.17. By this Spirit they crucifie the fleſh with the affections and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14227:10"/>luſts; in this Spirit they liue, and in this Spirit they walke, Gal. 5.24, 25.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this <hi>Spirit beareth witneſſe to our ſpirits that we are the ſonnes of God,</hi> Rom. 8.16. The Lord doth ſeale vs and giue vs the earneſt of this Spirit, 2. Cor. 1.22. by this Spirit of promiſe, the earneſt of our inheritance he ſealeth vs, till we fully enioy the ſame, Epheſ. 1.13, 14. and by this Spirit that dwelleth in vs, we know that God abideth in vs, 1. Ioh. 3.24.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the elect after their calling can boldly go to the throne of grace, there finding grace and obtaining mercie in the time of need, Heb. 4.16. yea by faith in Chriſt haue boldneſſe and acceſſe with confidence, Epheſ. 3.12. Gods children recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Spirit of Adoption, crie, <hi>Abba, Father,</hi> Rom. 8.15. For this end God ſendeth them the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his Sonne, that they may call God, <hi>Father,</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. 4.6. Gods Spirit helping our infirmities; teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs to pray, Rom. 8.26. The Lord powres on his Ieruſalem, the Spirit of grace and ſupplication, prayers for the forgiueneſſe of ſinne, Zac 12.10.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, this Spirit comforteth his in all diſtreſſes, when our ſpirits faile, God doth quicken vs by his good Spirit, Pſal. 143.7. He will not haue our ſpirits faile before him, Iſay 57.16. Therefore Gods Spirit is called <hi>the Comforter,</hi> Ioh. 14.16. and 15.26. and 16.7.</p>
            <p>The fourth reaſon is drawne from two honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble titles which are beſtowed on the faithfull, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>4</label> namely, 1. Gods Church; 2. Chriſts Spouſe. Theſe holy men and women are called <hi>Mount Sion, the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14227:11"/>of the liuing God,</hi> Heb 12.22. <hi>Segullah, Gods choiſe treaſure,</hi> Exod. 19.5. <hi>A peculiar people,</hi> Tit. 2.14. The viſible congregations, for the elects ſake are called <hi>the aſſembly of Saints,</hi> 1. Cor. 14.33. And God is called <hi>the King of Saints,</hi> Reu. 15.3. Theſe taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles are beautifull, Pſal. 84.1. <hi>How goodly are thy tents, O Iacob, and thy tabernacles, O Iſrael,</hi> Num. 24.5. The Church is <hi>faire as the Moone, cleare as the Sun, terrible as an armie with banners,</hi> Cant. 6.9, 12. My heart did ſet me on the chariots of my noble peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Ammi nadis,</hi> of whom I thinke nobly, people of good deuotions and noble reſolutions, Pſalme 110.3. They are renewed in the ſpirit of their minds, and haue put on the new man, which is created in knowledge, holineſſe and righteouſnes, Epheſ. 4.23, 24. Col. 3.10.</p>
            <p>The ſecond honorable title is, that the Church is called the Spouſe of Chriſt; <hi>At the Kings hand ſtandeth the Queene in a garment of Ophir,</hi> Pſal. 45.9. <hi>She is all glorious within,</hi> verſe 13. The bridegroom Chriſt in the fourth of the Canticles diſplayeth at large the honour and beautie of the Church; and in Cant. 6.8, 9. affirmeth, that all the Queenes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines and damoſels did praiſe her, being the only vndefiled of her mother. <hi>Salomons</hi> mother ſitteth at his right hand, 1. King. 2.19. ſo doth Chriſts Church, being clothed with the Sunne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, the light of the Moone at her feete, and a crowne of twelue ſtarres at her head, Reuelat. 12.1. Mal. 4.2. In this world Chriſt calleth her <hi>Chephſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah, My delight is in her,</hi> Iſay 62.4. Here ſhe is Ladie <hi>Sarah</hi> with her bond-woman <hi>Hagar</hi> attending on
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14227:11"/>her, Gal. 4.22. Gen. 2.19. How honorable ſhall ſhe be in heauen, when ſhe ſhall be preſented to God without ſpot or wrinkle, Epheſ. 5.27.</p>
            <p>The fift argument is thus framed: Noble-men haue vſually great inheritances, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>5</label> large poſſeſſions, rich offices, or liue on the bountie of their noble friends and allies. The faithfull in this reſpect ſing with <hi>Dauid, The Lord is the portion of mine inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and of my cup, thou ſhalt maintaine my lot; the lines are fallen to me in pleaſant places, yea I haue a goodly heritage,</hi> Pſal. 16.5, 6. By Chriſt we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted in an inheritance incorruptible and vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that fadeth not away, but is reſerued for vs in heauen, 1. Pet. 1.4. This better then the bleſſings of <hi>Iudahs</hi> wine, <hi>Aſers</hi> fatneſſe, or <hi>Ephraims</hi> dewes, Gen. 49.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0, 25. Whether things preſent, or things to come, all are ours in Chriſt, 1. Cor. 3.22, 23. by him we are ioynt heires, Rom 17. by him we attaine to an inheritance with the Saints in life, Coloſſ. 1.2.</p>
            <p>The ſixt reaſon prouing the exccellent ſtate of Gods children, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>6</label> is drawn from the honorable guard and retinue waiting on them. Firſt, God himſelfe keepeth his Iſrael, and neither ſlumbreth nor ſlee peth, Pſal. 121.4. <hi>The Name of the Lord is a ſtrong tower, the righteous runneth vnto it, and are ſafe,</hi> Pro. 18.10. <hi>As the mountaines compaſſe Iſrael, ſo the Lord is round about his people for euer,</hi> Pſal. 125.2. God is in the midſt of the Church, therefore it ſhal not fall, Pſal. 46.5. <hi>Behold, the eyes of the Lord are vpon them that feare him, and ſuch as truſt in his mercie, to deliuer their ſoules from death, and keepe them aliue in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14227:12"/>famine,</hi> Pſal. 33.18, 19. yea <hi>his eares are open to their crie,</hi> and ſo he deliuereth them out of many affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Pſal. 34.15, 19. He deliuereth his out of ſixe troubles, and the ſeuenth ſhall not hurt them, Iob 5.19. He is a wall of fire about his; and he that tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth them, toucheth the apple of his eye, Zac. 3.5. Notable is Ieruſalems deliuerance from <hi>Zenache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribs</hi> rage, 2. King. 19.34. and notable was Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noples deliuerance from the barbarous Gohiſts <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Gaynes</hi> in <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> time, as the Church ſtory telleth vs: alſo by our like miraculous deliuerance from the gun-powder treaſon, it appeareth that <hi>he that dwelleth in the ſecret place of the Higheſt, abideth vnder the ſhadow of the Almightie,</hi> Pſal. 91.1. God the Father eſpecially committeth the ſafe keeping of his Church to our Captaine Chriſt Ieſus, Ioſ. 5.14. Thus Chriſt looked out of the pillar of fire, and troubled the Egyptian hoaſt, Exod. 14.24. This An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of Gods preſence, Iſay 63.9. of the Couenant, Mal. 3.1. conducted Iſrael through the wilderneſſe into Canaan, Exod. 33.1, 2. This our <hi>Michael</hi> and great Prince ſhall ſtand vp for his people, either in <hi>Antiochus</hi> his time, as <hi>Iunius,</hi> or in Antichriſt and the Turks time, as <hi>Graſerius</hi> and others thinke, Dan. 12.1. He alwayes walkes in the midſt of the golden candleſticks, Reu. 2.1. Chriſts vineyard, which is his owne, is euer before him, Cant. 8.12. He watereth it euery moment, and keepeth it day and night, Iſay 27.2, 3.</p>
            <p>Next to Chriſt conſider the Angels vnder God and Chriſt, our protectors: <hi>The Angell of the Lord incampeth round about them that feare him, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14227:12"/>them,</hi> Pſal. 34.7. He giues his Angels charge to carrie vs in their hands, in all our wayes, Pſal. 91.11. Our Angels do alwayes behold the face of our heauenly Father, at his becke to come to our ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, Mat. 18.10. All theſe are miniſtring ſpirits, ſent forth to miniſter to them that ſhall be heires of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, Heb. 1.14. Not now viſibly appearing to teach, as before Chriſts time; nor viſibly to aſſiſt vs, as when they met <hi>Iacob,</hi> Gen. 32.1, 2. to encourage him againſt his brother <hi>Eſaw;</hi> for which their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, the place was rightly called <hi>Mahanaim,</hi> camps, that the Archangell Chriſt for a time taking vp the bodie of a man, wreſtled with <hi>Iacob,</hi> Geneſ. 32.24. when the place was called <hi>Peniel,</hi> the face of the ſtrong God. Theſe Angels ſeeing our conuerſion, do reioyce, Luk. 15.10. wondring at the manifold wiſedome of God, Eph. 3.10. do with bended knee prie into the myſterie of the Goſpel, 1. Pet. 1.12. As they comforted Chriſt after his temptations; and an Angell did ſtrengthen Chriſt in his agonie, Luk. 22.43. ſo Angels may aſſiſt vs in our corporall and ſpirituall combats, Epheſ. 6.12. <hi>Solomons</hi> night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of threeſcore the moſt valiant men in Iſrael, not like theſe, Cant. 3.7. One prayer of Chriſt drew more then twelue Legions of theſe heauenly ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers preſently at once, euery Legion did amount to about 7000. of horſe and foote, Math. 26.53. When one Angell could deſtroy in one night one hundred, foure ſcore and fiue thouſand, 2. King. 19.35. When <hi>Eliſha</hi> had prayed, his man could ſee mountains full of horſes and chariots of fire, 2. Kin. 6.17. Laſtly, God giueth to his Church, <hi>children,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14227:13"/>Princes in all lands,</hi> Pſal. 45.16. who by their lawes and ſwords defend the Church, and therefore are called <hi>nurſing fathers,</hi> Iſay 49.23. who by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment are a terror to the wicked, not to the godly, Rom. 13.3. Though ſometimes <hi>Nimrod</hi> be a mightie hunter before the Lord, Gen. 10.9. and ſome by the ſpoile of nations, get them wealth and honour, Iſay 10.7. Foure great beaſts, Dan. 7.3, 4. out of the laſt beaſt aroſe the double furious beaſt Antichriſt, riſing from the ſalt Clergie to his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall power, and earthly temporaltie to his tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall eſtate, Reu. 13.1.13. This was onely to puniſh the ſinnes of the Church. The end of true magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie from God is, that the Church vnder them may leade a quiet and peaceable life, in all godlineſſe and honeſtie, 1. Tim. 2.2.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth argument to proue the godlies dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>7</label> is drawne from their honorable ſeruices done for God and his people; the noble conqueſts they get, where their renowned trophees are erected, and doe ride in triumph in the tongues of good men. Thus the remnant of <hi>Iacob,</hi> in the middeſt of many people, become <hi>as the dewes from the Lord, as the rain on the graſſe,</hi> Mica 5.7. Theſe men ſometime ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due kingdomes, waxe valiant in fight, and turne to flight the armies of the alients, Heb. 11.33, 34. Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> with his trained or catechized ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, deſtroyed foure Kings, and deliuered <hi>Lot,</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ. 14.14. Thus <hi>Ioſua</hi> diſcomfiteth Amalek with the edge of the ſword, Ioſ. 17.9. What ſhall I ſpeake of <hi>Barak</hi> and <hi>Debora,</hi> of Zebulum and Nepthalim, that ieoparded their liues in the high places of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14227:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>field, Iudg. 5.18. What ſhall I ſpeake of <hi>Gedeon</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the Kings of Midian, Iudg. 7. and 8. of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> Iudg. 14.15.16. of <hi>Dauid,</hi> 2. Sam. 8. <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat,</hi> 2. Chron. 20.24. What ſhall we ſay of the <hi>poore wiſe man which by his wiſedome deliuereth a city,</hi> Eccleſ. 9.15. What ſhall wee ſay of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> Chriſts Generall in the Churches warre, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed <hi>Diocleſian, Maximianus, Maxentius</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinnius,</hi> making them by his ſword to flie from the feare of the Lambe, Reuel. 6.15.16. whom <hi>Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> ſuppoſeth to be that child (Reuel. 12.5.) who did bind the Dragoniſh pagan Emperours, Reuel. 20.1, 2. What ſhall I ſay of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> who ſlue the two tyrants <hi>Maximius</hi> and <hi>Eugenius,</hi> who had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore killed <hi>Valentinians</hi> two ſonnes, to whom the Poet <hi>Claudian</hi> ſingeth, <hi>O nimium dilecte Deo,</hi> Oh greatly beloued of God, whom the winds did ſerue in his warres. Let <hi>Belizarius, Virig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Ziſca</hi> the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemian ſcourge of the Pope, <hi>Iohannes Huniades, Scanderbeg</hi> be remembred; our martiall <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the hammer of the Pope and Papiſts; and ancient <hi>Effleda Merciorum Domina,</hi> the whipper of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Danes. <hi>Sed omnes non poſſumus eſse Scipiones aut Maximi,</hi> All cannot be <hi>Scipioes</hi> or <hi>Maximeſses,</hi> but yet they can by prayer with <hi>Moſes</hi> preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Amalek, Exod. 17.12. and with the ſame <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſtand in the gap, to turne away wrath from Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, pſal. 106.23. The good man in a generall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of manners, maketh vp the hedge by his prayers, Ezek. 22.30. Alſo this righteous mans lips by wholeſome exhortations feeds many, Pro. 13.21. For this cauſe <hi>Eliſha</hi> calleth <hi>Elias, The charets and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14227:14"/>horſmen of Iſrael,</hi> 2. Ki. 2.13. and King <hi>Ioaſh</hi> weeping on <hi>Eliſhas</hi> face a dying, calleth him his <hi>Father,</hi> calling him alſo <hi>the charets and horſemen of Iſrael,</hi> 2. Kin. 13.14. Theſe men fight againſt the diuell &amp; the world, Epheſ. 6.12, 13. by faith obtaine victorie, 1. Ioh. 5.3. they by Chriſt conquer Satan, Ioh. 16.23. treading him vnder their feete, Rom. 16.20. by whom they are more then conquerours, Rom. 8.38. Theſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Chriſtians do <hi>crucifie the fleſh with the affections and luſts,</hi> Gal. 5.24. And thus they get a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, God and the Church witneſſing their works, Heb. 11.4, 5. as it is ſpoken of <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Enoch.</hi> Thus their good name is better then ointment, Eccleſ 7.1. Thus Chriſts Name is like an ointment powred out, Cant. 1.3. Chriſt and his Churches name ſhall be remembred for euer, Pſal. 45.17. <hi>Pilates</hi> wife calleth Chriſt <hi>that righteous man,</hi> Math. 27.19. and <hi>Herod</hi> himſelfe reuerenced <hi>Iohn</hi> for his holineſſe and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, Mark 6.20. Theſe noble generous ſpirits manage noble exploits: <hi>Dauid hath ſlaine his thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands,</hi> 1. Sam. 20.17. <hi>Many daughters haue done well, thou excelleſt them all,</hi> Pro. 31.29.</p>
            <p>The eight reaſon is drawne from thoſe eſpeciall graces which are onely proper to the elect. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>8</label> Firſt, they onely truly know God, and whom he hath ſent, Chriſt, Ioh. 17.3. They haue iuſtifying faith, Tit. 1.1. which is more precious then gold, 1. Pet. 1.17. They haue <hi>hope that maketh not aſhamed,</hi> Rom. 5.3. by which they are ſaued, Rom. 8.25. by which they ſit in heauen, Epheſ. 2.6. being an anker-hold of the ſoule, firme and ſtedfaſt, by which they enter within the vaile, Heb. 6.9. They haue loue, both
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14227:14"/>towards God begetting, and his children begotten of him, 1. Ioh. 5.1. by which they know they are tranſlated from death to life, 1. Ioh. 3.14. They haue peace of conſcience, being iuſtified by faith, Rom. 5.1. which Chriſt giueth to his onely, Ioh. 14.27. which peace paſſeth all vnderſtanding, Phil. 4.7. <hi>A white ſtone, that none knoweth but he that hath it,</hi> Reu. 2.17. They haue ioy moſt glorious and vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, 1. Pet. 1.8. They are eſcaped from the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is in the world through luſts, and are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the diuine nature, 2. Pet. 1.4. are ſanctified wholy in ſpirit, ſoule and bodie, 1. Theſſ. 5.23. They are clothed with humilitie and patience, 1. Pet. 3.6. Iam. 5.8. Laſtly, they haue the Spirit of grace and deprecation, Zac. 12.10.</p>
            <p>The ninth reaſon is, that God bleſſeth to them euery eſtate of life, and death it ſelfe. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>9</label> 
               <hi>All things work together for good to them that loue God,</hi> Rom. 8.28. <hi>A little that the righteous hath, is better then great poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsions of the wicked,</hi> Pſal. 37.16. Prou. 16.8. Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is bleſt vnto them: <hi>Riches increaſing, their hearts are not ſet on them,</hi> Pſal. 62.10. By grace a brother in high degree can be humble, Iam. 1.9. <hi>Wiſedome with an inheritance together, maketh him excellent,</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. 7.11. <hi>Solomons</hi> wiſedome remained with him in proſperitie, Eccleſ. 2.9. The aduerſitie of the righteous is bleſſed to him, who after the endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of tentations, receiueth a crowne of glory, Iam. 2.12. Their ſufferings are bleſſed, Mat. 5.10. <hi>Bleſſed are the perſecuted for righteouſneſse ſake, for theirs is the kingdome of heauen.</hi> Thus Gods children made partakers of Chriſts ſufferings, reioyce, 1. Pet. 4.13.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14227:15"/>
               <hi>For light and momentanie afflictions, they reape an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and eternall weight of glorie,</hi> 2. Cor. 4.17. <hi>They are not worthy the glory that ſhall be reuealed,</hi> Rom. 8.18. Yea <hi>the death of the Saints is precious in Gods ſight,</hi> Pſal. 116.15. To them Death is deſtroyed, Hoſ. 13.14. and <hi>the ſting of death taken away,</hi> 1. Cor. 15.55, 56. <hi>Bleſſed are theſe dead that die in the Lord, for hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, ſo ſaith the Spirit, they reſt from their labours, and their works follow them,</hi> Reu. 14.13.</p>
            <p>The laſt argument proueth the poſteritie of the righteous to be bleſſeed, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>10</label> when the Lord becometh the God of our ſeed alſo, Gen. 17.7. The ſeed of the righteous ſeldome or neuer beg their bread, Pſal. 37.26. For <hi>Dauids</hi> ſake <hi>Solomons</hi> poſteritie are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, 1. King. 11.35. Pſal. 112.2.</p>
            <p>Firſt, this ſerueth to teach the righteous man thankfully to acknowledge his happie ſtate here, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> but eſpecially in the life to come. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that walketh not in the counſell of the vngodly, nor ſtandeth in the way of ſinners, and hath not ſat in the ſeate of the ſcornfull,</hi> Pſal. 1.1. <hi>Bleſſed are all that feare the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 112.1. <hi>Bleſſed are the vndefiled in the way, and walke in the law of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 119.1. What though mad men eſteeme thy life folly, and thy end ignominious, when thou art reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſonnes of God, and thy lot is among his Saints. What though the ſonnes of baſe men make thee their ſong, Iob 30.8, 9. yea count thee <hi>the of-ſcouring of the world,</hi> 1. Corin. 4.13. was not Chriſt ſo eſteemed amongſt the wicked? Mar. 15.28. Let it ſuffice thee that thou with Chriſt, through Chriſt art glorious in the eyes of God, Iſay 49.5.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14227:15"/>What though thou art an abhomination to the wicked? ſo let him be to thee, Pro. 29.27.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> ſeeing all men naturally deſire happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and honour, though they miſſe in the meanes of obtaining it; let all that follow after righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hearken vnto me, and that ſeeke the Lord, Iſay 51.1. <hi>Come ye children, hearken vnto me, I will teach you the feare of the Lord,</hi> pſal. 34.11. And which is the true way to honour and happineſſe the Lord himſelfe to man ſheweth what is good, Mica 6.8. If by patient continuing in well doing, thou ſhalt ſeeke for glorie, and honour and immortalitie, thou ſhalt find eternall life, Rom. 2.7. <hi>Let him that is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, be righteous ſtill,</hi> Reu. 22.11. <hi>The path of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is like the ſhining light, that ſhineth more and more to the perfect day,</hi> prou. 4.18. Canſt thou abaſe thy ſelfe for thy God, be ſtill more humble, he will aduance thee, and thou ſhalt be had in honour in the eyes of Gods ſeruants, 2. Sam. 6.22. For <hi>thoſe that honour God, he will honour; and they that deſpiſe God, ſhall be like eſteemed,</hi> 1. Sam. 2.30. Conſider the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Haman</hi> and <hi>Mordecay; Thus ſhall it he done to the man whom the King delighteth to honour,</hi> Heſt. 6.9.</p>
            <p>Eccleſ. 7.16. <hi>Be not ouer righteous, </hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> 7.16. <hi>neither make thy ſelfe ouer wiſe; why ſhouldſt thou deſtroy thy ſelfe? He that refraineth from euill, maketh himſlfe a prey,</hi> Iſay 59.15. If thou be too zealous, thy friends will think thee mad, Mark 3.21.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> that ſome thinke that raſh and rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous iudgement is here condemned, as Mat. 7.1. <hi>Iudge not, and ye ſhall not be iudged;</hi> and Iam. 3.1. <hi>Be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14227:16"/>not many maiſters.</hi> Others thinke, that men are not to ſtand too ſtiffe to the maintenance of their owne right, as <hi>Nabaoth</hi> did to the loſſe of his life, 1. King. 21.13. It may be thought he did well in denying the ſale of the inheritance of his fathers, when by Gods law the land was not to be alienated from the proper Tribes and owners till Chriſts coming, as may appeare in the caſe of <hi>Zelophehads</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Numb. 27.1. and in the caſe of raiſing ſeed to the deceaſed brother without iſſue, Deut. 25.5. <hi>Ruth</hi> 4.4. They all held their land of God <hi>in Capite,</hi> and could not ſell it for euer, but till the yeare of Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, Deut. 15.7, 8. Leu. 25.23, 24. od was their Lord Paramount. Thirdly, ſome interprete it thus: Be not phariſaically and hypocritically righteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, when God knoweth your hearts that they are abhominable, Luke 16.15. But I think it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for ſuperſtitious righteouſneſſe, a ſinne on the right hand, when men go beyond the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, keeping mens traditions, Mat. 15.3. Mar. 7.3. Col. 2.22.23. To Gods law nothing muſt be added nor taken away, Deut. 4.2. That we may be truly righteous, let vs conſider theſe motiues.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if we be holy and righteous, we are like our heauenly Father, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. We are ſecondly like vnto Chriſt, Acts 4.27. Acts 3.4. he was iuſt and holy. Thirdly, if we be holy, <hi>the Spirit of glorie and God reſteth on vs,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.16. his ſanctifying Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit reigneth in vs, Rom. 8.9. Fourthly, if we be holy and iuſt, we are the redeemed of the Lord, Luk. 1.75 Gal. 1.4. Fiftly, if not holy, not enter into Gods kingdome, Heb. 12.14. Reuel. 21.27. Sixthly, if
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14227:16"/>holy and righteous, we ſhall be bleſſed in our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eſtate. <hi>The wicked are ouerthrowne, are not, but the houſe of the righteous ſhall ſtand,</hi> Prou. 12.7. <hi>The righteous</hi> may <hi>fall ſeuen times a day, and be raiſed vp againe, but the wicked fall into miſchiefe,</hi> Prou. 24.16. <hi>When the righteous fall, the Lord putteth vnder his hand,</hi> pſal. 37.24. as the ſtanders by are wont to do, to ſaue a great mans ſonne from a fall in wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Outward things happen alike, to him that ſweareth,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>and to him that feareth an oath,</hi> Eccleſ, 9.12.</p>
            <p>Go thou into Gods ſanctuarie, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> and thou ſhalt ſee how the wicked in the beſt of their proſperitie ſtand in ſlippery places, and paſſe away as a dreame, pſal. 73.18.20. They flouriſh as a greene bay tree, and are ſoone cut downe. Marke the end of the iuſt and vniuſt, pſal. 37.35, 37, 38. The wicked flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as graſſe, are ſoone cut downe, pſal. 92.7. they iumpe fearfully into the graue, Iob 21.13. Laſtly, conſider that <hi>the righteous ſhall ſhine as the Sunne in the kingdome of their Father,</hi> Mat. 13.43.</p>
            <p>Secondly, conſider we the meanes of ſtirring vs vp to godlineſſe. Firſt, looke on the holineſſe and righteouſneſſe of God, which made the Angels to ſing, <hi>Holy, holy, holy is the Lord,</hi> Iſay 6.3. <hi>the earth is full of his glorie. Bleſſed be the glorie of the Lord from his place,</hi> Ezek. 3.12. <hi>He hath no pleaſure in wickednes, he hateth all the workers of iniquitie,</hi> pſal. 5.4, 5. <hi>His eyes are purer then to behold iniquitie</hi> without diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, Hab. 1.13. Secondly, obſerue the puritie and perfection of Gods law, it <hi>is perfect and giueth light to the ſimple,</hi> pſal. 19.7. it <hi>is a lampe to our feete, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14227:17"/>a light to our paths,</hi> pſal. 119.105. <hi>Ye are cleane</hi> (ſaith Chriſt, Ioh. 15.3.) <hi>by my word.</hi> Thirdly, propound to thy ſelfe the example of good men, Heb. 11. from verſe 2. to the end. <hi>Take, my brethren, the Prophets for examples. Behold the patience of Iob,</hi> Iam. 5.10.11. Look on <hi>Dauids</hi> zeale, pſal. 132.12. Let women looke on old holy Matrons, who truſted in God; looke on <hi>Sarah,</hi> calling her Huſband <hi>Lord, whoſe daughters ye are,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5, 6.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, remoue the impediments that cleaue to thy corrupt nature, and preſſe thee downe, Heb. 12.1. Firſt, ſuſpect that traitor in thine owne boſom: <hi>The heart of man is deceitfull aboue meaſure, and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly wicked,</hi> Ier. 17.10. <hi>Beware of an euill heart of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe, leſt your heart be hardned by the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne,</hi> Heb. 3.13. Secondly, beware of Satans temptations, being <hi>ſubtil ginnes and craftie deuices,</hi> 2. Cor. 2.11. and in Epheſ. 6.11. <hi>cunning tricks, and the fiery darts of the wicked one,</hi> Epheſ. 6.16. which are ſudden iniections to blaſphemie or deſperation.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, the firſt outward impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the world, wholy lying in ſinne, 1. Ioh. 5.19. In the world we may find the luſts of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life, 1. Ioh. 2.16. The ſecond outward let, is the proſperitie of the wicked, and the often afflictions of Gods children. This trouble (Iob 21.7) offended <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſal. 73.2, 3. Ier. 12.1, 2. Hab. 1.12, 13. Hence the Atheiſt collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that it is in vayne to ſerue God, ſeeing proud men and contemners of God advanced; againſt which temptation the godly conferre together, and are ſtrengthned by God. A booke is written of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14227:17"/>them <hi>that feare him and feare him not. &amp;c. Mal.</hi> 3.15.16.17. The wicked ſhall be burnt <hi>as in an Ouen, when the Sunne of Righteouneſſe ſhall ariſe on the godly. Mal.</hi> 41.2.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, what be the ſignes that we are truely righteous; firſt in our ſelues the Spirit of Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, calling God <hi>Father,</hi> Rom. 8.15.16. <hi>His ſpirit cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifiyng our ſpirits, that we are his children.</hi> Secondly, the fruits of the Spirit, <hi>loue, ioy, peace, &amp;c. Golat.</hi> 5.22. the practiſe of true pietie and charitie, whereby we make our <hi>vocation and election ſure,</hi> 2. Pet. 1.10. Election is firſt in natures order, but Gos vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is firſt knowne to vs. Marke laſtly theſe two eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all tokens of true ſinceritie: the firſt, loue to good men and ſuch as excell in vertue, Pſal. 16.2. <hi>By which we knowe that wee are tranſlated from death to life,</hi> 1. Ioh. 3.14. The ſecond is a delight in Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, Pſal. 19.10. <hi>the word of God is ſweeter then honie, better then gold.</hi> Iſa. 58.13.14 <hi>the Sabboth is the good mans delight. Gods precepts are not greiuous to him.</hi> 1. Ioh. 5.3.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> heere is an vſe of conſolation to the deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed children of God, <hi>they are glorious in Gods eyes,</hi> Eſa. 49.5. <hi>they are his cheife treaſure,</hi> Exod. 19.5. <hi>a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar people, honourable Kings and preiſts, that ſhall raign with Chriſt for euer.</hi> Reu. 5.10. This made <hi>Moſes</hi> to deſpiſe Aegipts glorie and riches, eſteeming the reproach of Chriſt much better, Heb. 11.25.26. <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing reſpect to the recompence of reward.</hi> This <hi>crowne of righteouſnes</hi> comforted <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. Tim. 5.7.8.</p>
            <p>You haue heard before in the opening of the ſence, that by the figure <hi>meioſis,</hi> more was meant
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14227:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>then ſpoken, That there is no excellencie to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous and vnregenerate; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>2</label> ſo continuing, God may ſay to them as <hi>Iacob</hi> to <hi>Reuben,</hi> Gen. 49.4. <hi>Thou ſhalt not be excellent;</hi> and as it was ſpoken in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſence, 1. Sam. 4.21. <hi>Ichabod,</hi> there is no glorie to them that continue in the baſeneſſe of vnrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate nature, which cometh ſhort of the glorie of God, that glorious Image that <hi>Adam</hi> loſt, Rom, 3.23. Gen. 1.26, 27. Theſe ſeeke not the recouerie of their loſt eſtate, for glorie, honour and true im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie, Rom. 2.7. They may be for their race as noble as <hi>Cain,</hi> but for ſinne curſed out of Gods preſence, carry a marke of baſeneſſe ſeene to God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.12.19, 20. God doth <hi>thraſh away all the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly of the earth like droſſe,</hi> Pſal. 119.119. They are called, <hi>witches children, the ſeed of the adulterer and whore,</hi> Iſay 57.3. <hi>Iohn</hi> calls them a <hi>generation of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> Mat. 3.7. and Chriſt, Mat. 23.33. a <hi>generation of ſerpents,</hi> for whom Hell is prepared. Ier. 6.28.30. <hi>braſſe, iron, lead, reprobate ſiluer.</hi> Pſal. 12.8. <hi>Zuloth,</hi> the wicked are termed <hi>a vile thing;</hi> and Pſal. 15.4. he is called <hi>a vile perſon.</hi> Pſal. 49.12. <hi>Adam Balialiu, did not reſt one night in his honour,</hi> or <hi>continued not long:</hi> and verſe 20. <hi>A man in honour, and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not, is like the beaſts that periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let vs ſee the reaſons that may further proue the baſeneſſe of the wicked.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> whereas the godly fetch their pedigree from God and heauen; the wicked deriue their race from the baſe earth below, and from the Diuell. Chriſt, to the vnbeleeuing reprobate Iewes, telleth them, Ioh. 8.44. that <hi>they are of their father the diuell,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14227:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>whoſe workes they do:</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Eph. 2.3. calleth ſuch <hi>the children of wrath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The wicked vnbeleeuers cannot call Chriſt their <hi>redeeming Kinſman,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> Iob 19.25. He doth not <hi>make them free,</hi> Ioh. 83.6. neither doth he <hi>pray for the world,</hi> Ioh. 17.9. They are none of that <hi>glorious Church</hi> that ſhall be one day <hi>without ſpot or wrinkle,</hi> Epheſ. 5.27.</p>
            <p>The third reaſon to proue their baſeneſſe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> that they are not guided by Gods Spirit, but are <hi>ruled by the ſpirit of the aire, working in the children of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience,</hi> Eph. 2.2. the diuel <hi>holds them in his ſnares,</hi> 2. Tim. 2.26. yea they are the <hi>bondmen of errruption,</hi> 2. Pet. 2.19. on theſe <hi>Cains</hi> marke is ſet, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.15. and either they haue a tormenting conſcience, as <hi>Saul,</hi> 1. Sam. 16.14. or <hi>Iudas,</hi> Math. 5.27. or a ſeared conſcience, 1. Tim. 4.12. Theſe, like condemned <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> ſee not the Kings face, Heſt. 7.8. Theſe <hi>crie not to God when he bindeth them,</hi> Iob. 36.13. as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane cuſtome was; and ours is to bind the hands of the condemned, i. <hi>Lictor, ligamans,</hi> go Sergeant binde his hands. <hi>Abner</hi> was not ſo bound, 2. Sam. 23.4. Theſe men forſaking God, are iuſtly of him forſaken in their miſeries, Prouerbs 1.26. He will no way anſwer <hi>Saul,</hi> 1. Sam. 28.6. Thus <hi>they flie when no man purſueth them,</hi> Prou. 28.1. <hi>fearing where is no feare,</hi> Pſalme 53.5. Dying either deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately like <hi>Iudas,</hi> Math. 27.5. or lumpiſhly and ſullenly like <hi>Nabal,</hi> 1. Sam. 25.37, 38. like a man cloſely murthered, and ſecretly throwne into Tems in a cloak-bag.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:14227:19"/>
            <p> Laſtly theſe men liue and dye in the bond of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, <hi>and gall of bitternes.</hi> Act. 8.23.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>4</label> what are theſe wicked men to the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie of the Saints, <hi>but as the blacke Tents of Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar, Pſal.</hi> 120.5. <hi>Tents of vngodlineſs,</hi> Pſal. 84.10. <hi>The Synagogues of Sathan,</hi> Reu. 2.9. <hi>Oh my ſoule come not thou into their ſecret, vnto their aſſemblies let not my glory be vnited,</hi> Gen. 49.6.</p>
            <p>The reprobates haue no right to any of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>5</label> Chriſt being the heire of the world, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2. &amp; by him <hi>all things are ours.</hi> 1. Cor. 3.22.23. They are vſurpers, <hi>their Table is a ſnare to them,</hi> Pſal, 69.22. Some of them are the ſonnes of villaynes, <hi>and eat Mallowes and Iuniper rootes,</hi> Iob, 20.4.5.6.7. Yea <hi>the Lions are</hi> ſometimes <hi>hunger-bitten,</hi> Pſal. 34.10. Laſtly, <hi>they haue no portion, no right, no memoriall in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> Neh. 2.20. nor inheritance in heauen, Reuel. 22.15. theſe <hi>dogs are without.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſixth reaſon, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>6</label> theſe are not vnder Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and guard of good Angels, but are in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans power their Iaylor, <hi>who worketh in them,</hi> Epheſ. 2.2. Heb. 2.15. <hi>who is their god,</hi> 2. Cor. 4.4. who like excommunicate perſons are deliuered to Satan, 1. Cor. 5.5. <hi>are in Satans bands,</hi> 2. Tim. 2.26. in worſe ſtate then Turkie gally ſlaues.</p>
            <p>But are not good Angels guardians of wicked States and Monarchies? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> Dan. 10.20. where the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell ſeemeth to attend the Princes of Perſia and Greece.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> that the preſeruing of publicke States for the Churches good, is one thing; and the guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of particular wicked men, is another: yet ſome
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14227:19"/>
               <hi>Cyrus</hi> for the future ſeruice of the Church, may be in a ſpeciall maner preſerued before he know God, Iſay 45.1.4. The iaylors and tormenters of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned are the diuels, Heb. 2.24, 25. 2. Pet. 2.4. Iude 6. who yet themſelues <hi>are kept in chaines of darkneſſe to the great iudgement day.</hi> I confeſſe that ſometimes for an <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſake an <hi>Iſhmael</hi> may thriue, Geneſ. 17.20. and may be preſerued ſtrangely by Gods An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, Gen. 21.7. But vſually I thinke that the Angels attendance on bad men, is like the guarding of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours and ſtrangers in Muſconia and China, who are chiefly waited on for feare of hurting the State; or like the Shiriffes men guarding the male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors to the gallowes.</p>
            <p>Though wicked-men may do ſome ſeruice for the Common weale, as <hi>Saul</hi> did, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>7</label> 1. Sam. 13.15. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> may be famous for bloodſhed, may be great hunters like <hi>Nimrod,</hi> Gen. 10.9. yet the end of theſe mens exploits is not to ſerue God and the Church herein, but they ſerue their owne luſts of couetouſneſſe and vainglorie. Theſe men could take cities and kingdomes, but could not rule their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is greater, Pro. 16.22. Therefore <hi>the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the iuſt is bleſſed, but the name of the wicked ſhall rot,</hi> Prou. 10.7.</p>
            <p>The reprobate hath no ſauing grace: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>8</label> 
               <hi>All haue not faith,</hi> 2. Theſſ. 3.2. Faith is onely Gods elect, Tit 1.1. The hope of the hypocrite is nothing, Iob 27.8 like a bulruſh, Iob 8.13. They are not freed from any ſin: <hi>Pride doth compaſſe them as a chaine,</hi> Pſal. 73.6. <hi>There is no peace to them,</hi> Iſay 48 22. and 57.21.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>9</label> theſe men are accurſed in euery thing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14227:20"/>they put their hands vnto, Deut. 28.16.17. accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in their liues and deaths: which cauſed <hi>Balaam</hi> to wiſh to <hi>die the death of the righteous.</hi> Numb. 23.10. Yea this curſe doth purſue their poſteritie, in the deſtruction of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> and <hi>Achabs</hi> houſe, 1. King. 14.20. 2. Kin. 10.10.</p>
            <p>The firſt vſe of this Doctrine is to diſcouer a double error in theſe men; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">vſe. </seg>1</label> firſt of their own eſtate; ſecondly of the condition of the godly. The wicked thinke themſelues happie and honorable, when they are baſe and miſerable, <hi>a wicked ſeed,</hi> Iſay 1.4. <hi>light as water, Gen.</hi> 49.3, <hi>like the beaſt that periſh,</hi> Pſal. 49.20. <hi>they thinke their ſtate and houſes ſhall continue for euer,</hi> Pſal. 49.18. and all this is becauſe often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>they haue no changes,</hi> Pſal. 55.29. Againe, theſe <hi>Iſhmaels</hi> mock <hi>Iſack</hi> that hath the promiſe, Gen. 21.9. they deſpiſe <hi>Dauids</hi> honour, Pſal. 4.2. they will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe him whom God will aduance, Pſal. 62.4. Theſe mad fooles <hi>mocke the counſell of the poore, truſting in God,</hi> Pſal. 14, 16. but God maketh them like a fiery ouen, ſuddenly ſhooteth at their faces, Pſalme 21.9.12.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">vſe. </seg>2</label> let this terrifie them, who <hi>becauſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt an euill worke is not ſpeedily executed, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet their hearts to do euill; Though a ſinner doth euill an hundred times, and God prolong his dayes, yet ſurely know that it ſhall go well to them that feare God, which feare before him, but it ſhall not be well to the wicked,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.11, 12, 13. theſe <hi>God ſcattereth as the winde doth the chaffe; they cannot ſtand in iudgement with the righteous,</hi> Pſal. 1.4, 5. they are <hi>tares bound vp for the fire,</hi> Mat. 13.30. theſe <hi>curſed</hi> muſt <hi>go to euerlaſting
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14227:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>fire,</hi> Math. 25.41. <hi>They ſhall leaue their names a curſe to Gods children,</hi> Eſa. 65.15. <hi>When they ſhall ſee</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſack <hi>and</hi> Iacob <hi>in heauen,</hi> Luke 13.28.</p>
            <p>Be you exhorted <hi>not to ſet your hornes on high,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>nor to ſpeake with a ſtiffe necke,</hi> Pſal. 75.5.</p>
            <p>THe ſecond clauſe of the verſe, the other branch of my Text, ſheweth the reaſon why men for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake true honour and follow baſe courſes, becauſe <hi>their proſperous way doth deceiue them.</hi> The <hi>way</hi> of the wicked, generally ſignifies their traine and courſe of life: <hi>The wayes of man are before the eyes of the Lord, and he pondereth their path,</hi> Prou. 5.21. <hi>God rendereth man according to his wayes,</hi> Ier. 17.10. <hi>God knoweth the way of the righteous, and the way of the vngodly ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi> Pſal. 1.6. Secondly, it ſignifieth the proſperity of their ways: <hi>Ieremie</hi> 12.1, 2. acknowledgeth Gods righteouſneſſe, yet wuld pleade with him concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his iudgements, <hi>Why doth the way of the wicked proſper? why are they happie that deale very trecherouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? The vngodly proſper in the world, and increaſe in riches,</hi> Pſal. 37.12. <hi>Tatzen ghem,</hi> doth deceiue them, and cauſeth them to erre in their wayes. <hi>Rabbi Elias</hi> thinketh that <hi>Tanguah</hi> written with the letter Teth, ſignifieth onely their errour of the mind; and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with Tau, as in this place, is onely to be referred to the errors of wayes and actions. This errour is confuted by comparing theſe two places together, Iſay 21.4. <hi>My mind erred;</hi> and Pſal. 119.110. <hi>I haue not erred from thy precepts;</hi> both are written with the letter Tau, and not Teth; yet the firſt ſpeaketh of the error of the mind, and the ſecond of the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14227:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>of wayes. <hi>Iunius</hi> tranſlateth this place thus, <hi>ſeducet eos,</hi> ſeduceth them, giueth this ſence: They erre in their falſe opinions, preferring themſelues before the iuſt, and moſt falſe by thinking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues more excellent then they. The French tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation thus, <hi>Les fera four<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er,</hi> will make them go aſtray. Let vs then vnderſtand this place of both theſe errors, thus: the proſperous way of wicked men, draweth their blind mind into a falſe conceit of themſelues and the righteous, and ſo cauſeth them to follow leud courſes. Now the error in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is more euident to vs; but becauſe the errour of the mind is for moſt in nature, and is the cauſe of the other, we will there begin.</p>
            <p>Now out of the coherence with the former clauſe, obſerue that here is a ſecret obiection an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; Why, if the righteous be ſo excellent, and the wicked ſo baſe, ſeeing all men hate baſeneſſe and loue honour, do not the wicked men become righteous, that they may alſo be excellent? The holy Ghoſt rendreth a ſtrong reaſon why they continue wicked ſtill: Their outward pompous eſtate blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth their iudgement and leadeth them aſtray. Hence gather with me theſe two Doctrines:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The proſperitie of the wicked maketh him a foole, in falſle iudging of his owne and the righteous mans eſtate.</hi> The ſecond is, that <hi>The wickeas proſperous eſtate can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them to erre from the paths of righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before we enter into the ſeuerall handling of theſe points, let vs remoue a ſcruple and doubt hence ariſing: That many forlorne wretches ſerue the diuell for nothing, and as they are baſe by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14227:21"/>of their ſinne before God, ſo are they miſerable in the ſight of the world, whom <hi>want and famine doth hunt to deſolate places, who feed on mallowes and iuniper rootes, dwelling in the clifts of the valleys, and are the ſonnes of villaines,</hi> Iob 30.3, 9. when on the contrary, <hi>the candle of the Lord ſhineth on Iobs head, yea when Iob waſhed his ſteps with butter, and riuers of oyle out of the rocke flowed to him, when yong men and old Princes honour Iob,</hi> Iob 29.3.12. theſe men haue no proſperous wayes to ſeduce them. For the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of which doubt, obſerue with me that all the diſputation of <hi>Iob</hi> with his three friends, from the fourth to the 32, handleth theſe points: firſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all wicked men are in this world ouertaken with Gods iudgements: ſecondly, whether the godly do alwaies here continue in their proſperitie: thirdly, whether <hi>Iob</hi> now falling into miſery, to be an hypocrite. <hi>Iobs</hi> falſe friends hold the affirmatiue part; and <hi>Iob</hi> by diuine arguments and experience holdeth the negatiue, ſtrongly prouing that by theſe outward things <hi>no man knoweth loue or hatred,</hi> as <hi>Salomon</hi> alſo teacheth, Eccles 9.1. and <hi>if our hope were onely of this preſent life,</hi> many of Gods children <hi>were of all men moſt miſerable,</hi> 1. Cor. 15.19. as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth. Herein Gods iudgements being moſt vnſearchable, <hi>like the great depth,</hi> Pſal. 36.6. which are ſecret, but alwayes iuſt, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth. Out of theſe things to the former obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I frame this anſwer, That although all the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked enioy not an heauen of ioys here, and all Gods children are not poore and of low degree, but ſome are honorable in the ſight of God and man, and do
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14227:22"/>
               <hi>increaſe in fauour with God and man,</hi> as it is ſpoken of Ieſus our Lord, Luk. 2.52. yet I affirme that not onely the rich <hi>Nabals</hi> and proud <hi>Hamans</hi> deſpiſe Gods children, but the very ſonnes of fooles and baſe men, whoſe fathers were not worthy to ſit with the dogs of <hi>Iobs</hi> flocke, do yet make <hi>Iob</hi> their ſong and by-word, Iob 30.1, 8, 9. yea Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was <hi>accounted a worme and no man, a reproach of men, and deſpiſed of the people,</hi> Pſal. 22.6. How were the Heathen wont to crie out againſt the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in time of perſecution, <hi>Haire atheous,</hi> Deſtroy theſe Atheiſts? How baſely did the poore landiner caſt off the loue and kindneſſe of his rich neighbor, as ſoone as he perceiued he did ſmell of the Goſpel; as our worthy in his Acts and Monuments ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. The vnconuerted theefe in the time of Chriſts paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was as buſie in reuiling Chriſt as the Scribes and Phariſees, Luk. 22.29. Yea, many thieues and murtherers thinke better of their leud courſes then of the wayes of the Lord, becauſe they ſee Religion euery where ſpoken againſt, Acts 28.22. If the matter were put, not onely to rich wicked men, but alſo to beggers, whether <hi>Barabbas</hi> or <hi>Chriſt</hi> were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be choſen in their hearts, they would rather chuſe a rebell and a robber then Chriſt, Ioh. 18.40. Acts 3.14. Mat. 27.16. Yea the baſeſt beggers do ſo diſtaſte Religion, that they eſteeme their eſtate bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the eſtate of the earneſt profeſſors. This obiection then notwithſtanding, it is plaine, that The proſperitie of wicked rich men ſeduceth them, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>1</label> blindfoldeth their iudgement ſo, that they thinke well of their deſperate eſtate, and in their hearts do
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14227:22"/>condemne the generation of the righteous. <hi>There is a way that ſeemeth right to a man, but the end thereof are the wayes of death,</hi> Prou. 14.2. The ſame parable for the excellencie thereof repeated in the ſame words, <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.25. <hi>The proſperous way of theſe ungodly ſeemeth at the firſt entrance faire vnto them, but the end thereof is deſtruction.</hi> Like <hi>the broad way and wide gate</hi> that Chriſt ſpake of, Mat. 7.13. Like a faire greene land, leading a traueller out of his way, and caſting him to the hands of theeues. <hi>Becauſe they haue no changes, they feare not God,</hi> Pſal. 73.20. This cauſed Chriſt, Mat. 13.22. to giue this epithete to riches, <hi>deceitfulneſs of riches,</hi> becauſe they do deceiue men, falſly perſwading them that they make them hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie; when <hi>Salomon</hi> telleth, Pro. 1.33. that <hi>the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of fooles deſtroyeth them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt reaſon proouing that proſperitie doth deceiue the wicked, ſhall be this: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> If Gods childrens <hi>feete be almoſt gone, and their ſteps do well neereſlide in ſeeing the proſperitie of the wicked,</hi> Pſal. 73.1, 2. and if <hi>the people do turne in hither, becauſe waters of a full cup are wrung out to theſe wicked;</hi> and if the godly in their weakneſſe do hereat ſay, <hi>I haue cleanſed my heart in vaine, and waſhed my hands in innocencie;</hi> and if the righteous are onely at this, for feare of <hi>condemning the generation of the righteous,</hi> and cannot be fully ſtrengthened againſt this temptation <hi>till they go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sanctuarie of God, to ſee how theſe wicked are ſet in ſlipperie places, and thence come to ſudden and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ruine,</hi> Pſal. 73.12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. how can it be but that the wicked themſelues not armed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe temptations, do bleſſe themſelues in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14227:23"/>their outward eſtate, <hi>hauing their portion onely in this world,</hi> Pſal. 17.14.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon ſtandeth thus: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> Riches to a wicked man, is an idol; and therefore the couetous is called an Idolater, Eph. 5.5. <hi>a teacher of lies,</hi> Hab. 2.18. Now <hi>the rich mans wealth is is ſtrong citie, and is an high wall in his conceit,</hi> Prou. 18.11. But in the verſe immediatly aforegoing, <hi>Salomon</hi> telleth, that <hi>the name of the Lord is a ſtrong tower, the righteous runneth to it and are ſafe;</hi> where the Antitheſis doth teach vs, that as the righteous truſt in God and are ſafe; ſo wicked men truſt in their god Mammon, and periſh, when their riches becometh a broken reed in their hands, Iſay 31.3. Though he ſnuffeth at men, and ſay in his heart, <hi>I ſhall neuer be moued,</hi> Pſa. 10.5, 6. yet by the miſerable euents they find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues deceiued; and as other idolaters haue fed on aſhes, and a ſeduced heart hath turned them aſide, I ſay 44.20. that they cannot deliuer their owne ſoules, nor ſay, <hi>Is there not a lie in my right hand?</hi> All idolaters are like the diſtempered ſtomacke of a woman with childe, or yong children, who will eate chalke and coales, and lime out of the wall. Whoredome, women and new wine take away mens hearts, when they ask counſell of their ſtocks, and their ſtaffe teacheth them, the ſpirit of forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation cauſeth men to erre, Hoſ. 4.11, 12. So the god Mammon, in whom theſe men truſt in ſtead of God, Mat. 6.24. deceiueth them of all ſpiritual ſence and vnderſtanding. Some do to this purpoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete that of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1. Tim. 6.5. <hi>Men deſtitute of truth,</hi> doe take gaine to be godlineſſe;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14227:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>or with <hi>Simon Magus</hi> would make gaine of a ſhew of godlineſſe, Acts 8.19, 20. If <hi>couetouſneſſe</hi> be <hi>the roote of all euill,</hi> 1. Tim. 6.19. then if this blind error which poſſeſſeth many <hi>Nabals</hi> with vs, who haue neither the knowledge nor power of godlineſſe, yet do thinke themſelues godly becauſe they are rich; and other good men to be irreligious, becauſe they be poore; like the Phariſees, Ioh. 7.49. theſe beggars know not the law, and are curſed.</p>
            <p>The third reaſon is this, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> becauſe the nature and qualitie of proſperitie vnſanctified becometh a ſnare, Pſal. 69.22. it maketh them high minded, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſth them to truſt in theſe vncertaine riches, and not in the liuing God, who giueth all things richly to enioy, 1. Tim. 6.17. Thus with <hi>Pharaoh</hi> they ſay in their hearts, <hi>who is the Lord that I ſhould obey him? I know not the Lord,</hi> Exod. 5.2. They bid God <hi>depart from them, they will learne none of his wayes,</hi> Iob 21.14. and with <hi>Nabal</hi> to puffe at Gods poore children, 1. Sam. 25.10. <hi>Who is Dauid? who is the ſonne of Iſhai? we haue too many of theſe runnagate beggers;</hi> but yet after, ver. 37, 38. when God ſmote him, his heart was dead as a ſtone, and ſo he went fullenly to his graue, as a hog drinking in his blood, or as a ſlaine man ſecretly in a cloakbag caſt into Thames.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, beſides this dotage, making them thinke that their <hi>houſes ſhall continue for euer,</hi> Pſal. 49.11.18. the flatteries of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> people doth much confirme their folly. As long as thou doeſt good to thy ſelfe, men will ſpeake well of thee. Liue thou, and ſpeake like the Epicure ſoule, Thou haſt enough laid vp in ſtore for many yeares, cate, drinke, and be merry;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14227:24"/>like <hi>Sardinapalus</hi> or <hi>Eligabalus,</hi> as I ate, ſo much I had; ſaying, Let vs eate and drinke, for to morrow we ſhall die, <hi>Eſay</hi> 22.13. Weare ſilke, fare deliciouſly euery day, like an oxe fatting thy ſelfe to the day of ſlaughter, go ſpeedily to hell, Luk. 16.19. yet flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers will ſay, Your Worſhip is wiſe; what ſhould you doe but <hi>iocundare cum amicis,</hi> and ſpend your time in pleaſures. How eaſily will theſe vaine flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries worke on fooliſh rich men, who with <hi>Adam</hi> follow vaine inuentions, Eccles 7.31. who become vaine in their <hi>imaginations,</hi> &amp; whoſe fooliſh heart is darkneſſe, Rom. 1.21 that walke in the vanitie of their mindes, hauing their cogitations darkened, Eph. 4.17, 18. who labour to extinguiſh the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the light of nature, withholding the truth in vnrighteouſneſſe, Rom. 1.18. Hence, the idolatrie of riches, the ſnare of riches, the flatterie of wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches increaſe in worldly rich men this their frenzie, the deceitfulneſſe of mens hearts, Ier. 17.9. the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſſe of riches, Mat. 13.22. the whole world lying in ſinne, 1. Ioh. 5.19. where is to be found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but theſe luſts of the fleſh, the luſts of the eyes, the pride of life, 1. Ioh. 2.15. drawing men to folly and ſinne, and when the diuell the god of this world, doth hoodwinke theſe mens eyes, that they cannot ſee, beleeue, and be ſaued, 2. Corinth. 4.3, 4.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">vſe. </seg>1</label> let this inſtruct thee, not to maruell to ſee ſo many rich men fatted againſt the day of ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who vpon a falſe perſwaſion go merily to hell, as the oxe to the ſhambles, like a foole to the ſtocks, Prou. 7.22. they flatter themſelues in their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14227:24"/>till their abhominations to be hated are found out, Pſal. 36.2. Thus their wayes ſhew their folly, yet their poſteritie approue their ſaying, Pſal. 49.13. Theſe mens wealth fooliſheth them, as blind zeale doth a Papiſt, Acts 13.50. who thinke to ſerue God in perſecuting his Church, Ioh. 16.2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> let me hence exhort theſe ſeduced ſoules not to truſt in vanitie, leſt vanitie be their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, Iob 15.31. Oh <hi>trust not in robberie; if ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches increaſe, ſet not your hearts on them,</hi> Pſal. 62.10. <hi>Let not your hearts be ouercome with the care of this life,</hi> Luk. 21.34.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> O ye rich men ſtop your eares againſt all flatterers, eſpecially ſuch as will feed you with ſweete words, crying, peace, peace, when all is naught, Ier. 14.13, 14. Theſe <hi>Syrens</hi> ſongs will caſt you on more dangerous gulfes then <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribdis.</hi> Vſe the world, as not abuſing, for the faſhion thereof leadeth men aſtray. Let our <hi>Purchas</hi> tell you of <hi>Atoadines</hi> fooles paradiſe, pag. 317. a Perſian Mahometan, who incloſed a goodly valley between two hils, filled with all pleaſure that nature or art could affoord them, he gaue at the firſt entrance to his youths a ſleepie drinke, caried them aſleep into his place of pleaſure, where they ſaw and enioyed many rarities; after, gaue them another ſleepie po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and then caried them out againe; and ſo theſe fooles thought they had beene in paradiſe; and in hope of this they were fleſhed for the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of any villanie; therefore <hi>Vtan</hi> the Turke after deſtroyed it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> let this comfort them that can vſe this
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14227:25"/>world aright; as fiſh are freſh in the ſalt Ocean, as <hi>Abraham, Dauid</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> who in abundance of riches ſerued God; and <hi>Salomons</hi> wiſedome in his proſperitie remained with him, Eccles 2.19. to him wiſedome with an inheritance was good, Eccles 2.11.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Doctrine out of the ſecond clauſe of my Text, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>2</label> is, That the proſperous way of wicked men doth make them follow ill courſes. The para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the prodigall ſonne, that neuer thought of his returne home to his father till he had ſpent all, proueth this, Luk. 15.14, 15, 16. A man in proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, not ſanctified, is like a wilde aſſe vſed to the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, <hi>that ſnuffeth in the aire at her pleaſure, at her occaſion who can turne her, all that ſeek her will be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, in her moneth you ſhall finde her when ſhe is pained in bringing forth her yong,</hi> Ier. 2.24. It is proſperitie that ſlayeth the foole, Prou. 1.32. If euer he will ſeeke the Lord, in affliction he will ſeeke him dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, Hoſ. 5.15. The erring wandrings of wicked rich men, is like <hi>Ioſephs</hi> loſing himſelfe in the field, Gen. 37.15. Proſperitie is like a falſe guide that ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a man out of his way at the firſt entring into his trauell, and ſo they walke through by-paths, Iudg. 5.6. <hi>Before I was afflicted I went aſtray,</hi> Pſal. 119.67. To wicked men <hi>their table is made a ſnare, and their proſperitie their ruine,</hi> Pſal. 69.21.</p>
            <p>The firſt reaſon to proue this, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> is an argument drawne from infallible experience in all ages, ſhewing that wealth and riches haue beene vſed as weapons of rebellion againſt the Lord. <hi>Ieſhurun</hi> that ſhould haue beene vpright, when he waxed far
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14227:25"/>kicked with his heele, Deut. 32.15. Wealth without grace, maketh prouiſion for the luſts of the fleſh, Rom. 13.14. Riches are conſumed on luſts, Iam. 4.3. Let vs examine ſome particulars: Firſt, wealth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the fat adulterers like fed horſes to neigh af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their neighbours wiues, Ier. 5.8. We haue a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full example in <hi>Dauid,</hi> 2. Sam. 11.2. Secondly, here men grow into idolatrie, as we ſee in <hi>Salomons</hi> time, 1. King. 11.23. when men doe richly endow and decke their idols, Pſal. 16.3. Thirdly, hence <hi>pride doth compaſſe them as a chaine,</hi> Pſal. 73.6. Fourthly, hence commeth blaſphemie, when <hi>they ſtretch out their tongues againſt heauen,</hi> that is, God in heauen, Pſal. 73.9. They ſay, <hi>Who is the Lord?</hi> Exod. 5.2. and they bid God depart from them, Iob 21.14. Wealth maketh men reiect the poore, reiect iuſtice; <hi>For mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> (ſay they) <hi>anſwers all things,</hi> Eccles 10.19. <hi>Bring</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that we may drinke,</hi> Amos 4.1. To main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their pompe and ſtate, they haue both their hands open, Mica 7.3.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> there are certaine adiuuant cauſes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king riches poiſonfull inſtruments of vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to men. There are two corrupters of the wealth without them; firſt, the diuell doth dazle mens eies with the glittering ſhew of wealth, 2. Cor. 4.4. as Lark-catchers do vſe their gloſſes to deceiue the ſilly bird. Secondly, the flatteries of the world are falſe bawdes to bewitch rich men, as <hi>Adullam</hi> was to <hi>Iudah,</hi> Gen. 38.20. Thirdly, within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, their owne falfe vnbeleeuing hearts deceiue them, Heb. 2.13. Here <hi>the way of wicked men is in darkneſſe, they know not at what they ſtumble,</hi> Prou.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14227:26"/>4.19. And thus alſo <hi>becauſe ſentence againſt an euill worke is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the hearts of the ſonnes of men is fully ſet to do euill,</hi> Eccles 8.11. and ſo with <hi>Diues</hi> go ſuddenly to hell, Luke 16.19, 20, 21.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine ſerueth firſt to terrifie the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Nabals</hi> of the world, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> to whom Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Wo be vnto you that are rich now, for you haue receiued your conſolation. Wo vnto you that are full, for you ſhall hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Wo vnto you that laugh now, for you ſhall mourne and weepe.</hi> Luk. 6.24, 25. To whom <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, Iam. 5.1, 2, 3. <hi>Go to now ye rich men, weepe and houle for the miſeries that ſhall come on you; your riches are corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and your garments are moth-eaten; your gold and ſiluer is cankerd, and the ruſt of them ſhall be a witneſse againſt you, and ſhall eate your fleſh as fire; you haue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped treaſures againſt the laſt dayes. Walke in the wayes of your owne heart, and in the ſight of your eyes, know that for this you ſhall come to iudgement,</hi> Eccles 11.9. <hi>Oh conſider this ye that forget God, leſt he come and teare you in peeces, and there be none to deliuer you,</hi> Pſal 50.22.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">vſe. </seg>3</label> let me hence exhort the wicked world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to <hi>ſtand in awe, and ſinne not; commune with your owne hearts on your beds, and be ſtill,</hi> Pſal. 4.4. Be not like bankrupts, who for feare of their great debts, dare not looke into their reckoning bookes. Oh <hi>breake off your ſinnes with righteouſneſſe, and your ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities with ſhewing mercie to the poore,</hi> Dan. 4.27. <hi>Be not high minded, ye rich men, truſt not in vncertaine riches, but in the liuing God, who giueth vs all things richly to enioy,</hi> 1. Tim. 6.17. But it may be that in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14227:26"/>vaine I ſpeake to moſt of theſe men; therefore in the third place I will direct my ſpeech to the holy and righteous man: Firſt, enuie not rich men in the riches they ſpend on their luſts, Iam. 4.3. Pſal. 37.1. When <hi>many ſay, who will ſhew vs any good?</hi> do thou ſay, <hi>Lord lift vp the light of thy countenance vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me;</hi> and, <hi>Thou haſt put more gladneſſe in my heart, then they that had their corne and wine increaſed,</hi> Pſal. 4.6, 7. <hi>A little that the righteous hath, is better then great poſſeſsions of the wicked,</hi> Pſal. 37.16. <hi>If God ſhall bring thee to houſes which thou buildeſt not, filled with all maner of ſtore, and thou eating art full, then take heed leſt thou forget the Lord thy God,</hi> Deut. 6.12, 13, 14. Laſtly, pray we with <hi>Agur,</hi> Prou. 30.8, 9. not for ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>leſt thou being too full, ſhould denie thy God;</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire onely bread of competencie, <hi>arton epiouſion,</hi> ſit both for quantite and qualitie to ſupport nature. Mat. 6.11. <hi>Let your conuer ſation be without couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for God will not forſake thee,</hi> Heb. 13.5. <hi>We brought nothing into this world, we ſhall carrie naught hence. If we haue food and raiment, let vs learne to be content. Rich men fall into temptations, ſnares, notſome luſts, drowning men in perdition,</hi> 1. Tim. 6.7, 8, 9. Math. 6.25. To this end remember theſe reaſons of Chriſt: firſt, he giueth thy body life; ſecondly, he feedeth rauens; thirdly, he clotheth lillies; fourthly, <hi>the Gentiles ſeeke after theſe things;</hi> fiftly, <hi>none can adde one cubite to his ſtature;</hi> ſixtly, are arguments of want of faith; ſeuenthly, <hi>ſufficient to the day is the trauell;</hi> eightly, <hi>firſt ſeek Gods kingdome and his righteouſnes, and all other things ſhall be caſt vpon you.</hi> When <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſought of God true wiſdome before all thing,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14227:27"/>God gaue him that and all other neceſſary bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings too, 2. Chron. 1.10, 11. So if we ſet our hearts on heauen, Col. 3.1. he will giue vs that, and for a ſurpluſſage all things neceſſary for the maintenance of this preſent life, 2. Pet. 1.3. Yea when thou ſhalt ſee ſeduced ſinners turned into hell, thou ſhalt find to thy comfort that God which hath here guided thee from theſe errors by his counſell, will in the end receiue thee to glorie through Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
